[SPEAKER_01]: Two things I was thinking about this week a bit.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of them was in relation to something you mentioned, or that was mentioned in the last weeks, when we were talking about a subha, because actually for me that's one of the... that's one of the contemplations that I've always found most difficult, in terms of understanding how to... how it should be done rightly.
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the reasons for that was because it always kind of came across as though it is supposed to be about, like, generating a kind of active... almost like hatred or revulsion towards the body.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I couldn't really get the...
[SPEAKER_01]: I didn't understand the point of that.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or whether... and I was not sure if it was really supposed to do that.
[SPEAKER_01]: But then you hear, like, for example, you were mentioning, like last week, the story of the monks who killed themselves because they practiced vasuva.
[SPEAKER_01]: And yet, I'm not sure if that's really the point to be, like, generating almost this, yeah, like I said, the kind of active revulsion or disgust.
[SPEAKER_00]: What do you mean by active?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, active is supposed more like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, revulsion, disgust, is the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: But it's how you do it and on what level you do it, then...
[SPEAKER_01]: I suppose, I suppose, I mean, like, almost an emotional reaction, whether it should be that or is it... because...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it reminded me as well of, like, something... Yeah, no, I know what you mean.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know what I mean?
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: And...
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's...
[SPEAKER_00]: I think, initially, it will be emotional, you know, it will have to be, because you... the pathway hasn't been trained sufficiently enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, yes, the more correctly it is done, less emotional it is.
[SPEAKER_00]: It becomes more precise.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, it starts to undermine only the lustful parts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Only the part that you're attracted, that you're gripped with attraction, that's undermined by lust, by asubha, that lust is undermined by it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not everything else.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you're not emotionally overwhelmed or disgusted with everything and nothing, and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think about it, a very specific food that you really want to eat, and you see no reason to not eat that.
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there are plenty of other food, but you have no desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have the same end result feeding your body, but particular type of food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you can say no to it, of course, each time, and not eat it, but you still remain attracted to it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, if you were to do a subha correctly, you would be finding ways, through contemplation,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's hard to undermine that specific desire towards that specific food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you wouldn't have to hate all the food.
[SPEAKER_00]: And you wouldn't have to be emotionally disgusted with eating altogether.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just this particular consumption of this particular food, you find disgust.
[SPEAKER_00]: You have to find disgust in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not just convincing yourself to not eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You actually have to undermine desire, and disgust in regard to the thing you desire, is what undermines the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, there is the active disgust, but it's not everywhere and nowhere, which it might be initially.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is why those monks did kill themselves, because they got overwhelmed, because they did not apply it where it's supposed to, precisely enough.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, that makes sense, because...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, think about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: There is your favorite plate with the favorite food on it, and then you find out somebody's patting it, or worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Would you have desired to eat that thing on the plate right in front of you?
[SPEAKER_00]: Still the same look, still the same smell, still the same taste.
[SPEAKER_00]: You probably wouldn't taste someone else's fluids in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But would you eat it now that you know that?
[SPEAKER_00]: You'll be quite disgusted.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if somebody were to put it in your mouth, that food, you would be like spitting it out, disgusted.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to have to swallow it, you would be disgusted.
[SPEAKER_00]: At any part of involvement with that food, that disgust would be there as a framework of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because now you know what's in it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, yeah, but that's quite a good... it is quite a good example, because it's like... that makes sense.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because the disgust, basically, only... it's like, yes, I would be disgusted in terms of... okay, yeah, I'm not eating that.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to eat it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't want to go near it.
[SPEAKER_01]: But that's where it ends, basically.
[SPEAKER_01]: Then, you don't need to kind of... go and carry that disgust with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: I don't know, like, you know... No, if you do, means you don't quite still see the basis where that lust is.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because then, like, if you're kind of going on about how disgusting it is, it's like, there's no need to.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's just, okay, I just don't need to touch it.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't need to be involved.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the disgust would be evoked if there is a careless mental tendency towards eating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you get reminded of the disgust implicit.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, obviously, initially, the whole picture is perverted.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's upside down.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start with the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: You start with the attraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, disgust has to be kind of contemplated into it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, to then become the normal, like, natural kind of...
[SPEAKER_00]: The first thing you would see, if you were to engage with it, would be disgust, as opposed to attraction, which was before the case.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, oh, I want this.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, oh, no, it's ugly, it's disgusting, and then you work, and then you work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But no, this comes up.
[SPEAKER_00]: Oh, it's the disgust part, comes up.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, then, that's like... Because in terms of, then, how
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, how I relate to the body, for example, in general.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay, if I need to go to the toilet, I need to go to the toilet.
[SPEAKER_01]: If I need to wash it, it needs to be washed.
[SPEAKER_01]: I need to kind of engage with it to a certain extent.
[SPEAKER_00]: But then...
[SPEAKER_00]: So, when would then... if you were to contemplate disgust rightly, when would that... when would then disgust arise in regard to your own body?
[SPEAKER_01]: Well, seeing it like if... seeing it as a, I don't know, an object of attraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Sexual attraction, for example.
[SPEAKER_00]: Sexual attraction, okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or in terms of, I don't know, like if somebody wants to decorate it or... Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to take it as a thing of beauty to be displayed.
[SPEAKER_01]: Displayed for others or something.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you were to use it as a basis for pleasure.
[SPEAKER_01]: In general.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: That disgust can undermine that as well.
[SPEAKER_00]: But, if the mind stops going in those directions, there is no disgust to be... certainly to be there, actively felt.
[SPEAKER_01]: And you... that's what I mean, like, you can engage with this without... in those kind of neutral ways.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: Without...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean...
[SPEAKER_00]: The ways that are not sexual, not vain, not about beautification, not about gaining pleasure through the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: Admire... being admired on the account of physical... that's also... again, that would be undermined by the disgust, by a subha.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or even, like, not... not necessarily, like, I want to be admired by others as a kind of a... as a human being in terms of being seen in a certain way by others.
[SPEAKER_01]: I think even that would be kind of undermined, no?
[SPEAKER_01]: By... because it's all kind of on the basis of this, well, bag of bones.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, I mean, yeah, sure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You could, yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: And I guess the other thing that, at least in the past, was not really clear, is like, clear for me, was how to
[SPEAKER_01]: Because it's often spoke about in terms of, like, how to practically go about doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Let's say, like, how do you contemplate a subhāna?
[SPEAKER_01]: And especially when it comes to, like, then, I don't know, there's this list of, like, internal organs and stuff.
[SPEAKER_01]: I don't know, to me, I think of an internal organ and my mind just is like, well, that's just something I'm imagining.
[SPEAKER_00]: I think for most people that's what it is, because that's why, like, when you look at these Sūbha contemplations done as methods and techniques, they just become this kind of empty recital of this visualized sort of abstract ideas that then people kind of implicitly hope will somehow cause passion to disappear from it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And, eh... and even, like, just... just looking at the asubha pictures and, eh... contemplating, like, you know, in the suttas, contemplate the bodies on the charnel ground and stuff.
[SPEAKER_00]: You realize, even that, you might get that initial shock, but then you get used to it, you overcome it, and you stop seeing it, and then the lust is back.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then now you're just... you're just numb to... to these... these shocking contemplations and sights and sounds and smells and so on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, if you're just applying it, kind of, as a blanket practice, but you don't see the relationship between that and the actual lust and attraction when it is present, it's not going to work, because you're not making the necessary connection between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, practically, you want to contemplate a subha, as I said, first,
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, in order to make the connection, so that the subha can be applied rightly on the things that can be undermined by it, you need to stop just habitually trying to get rid of those things when they arise.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if you do have a desire for a food on the plate, yes, you can't just start eating it, so you have to restrain.
[SPEAKER_00]: That also means you need to stop looking at it, smelling it, holding it, bringing it close to your face and so on, whatever you would... but I'm not eating it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, but you're doing everything else around it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you need to withdraw your senses from it and then the mental pressure on account of that desire, that's what you can... you have to endure now rightly, without going back to these objects.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if that endurance is done sufficiently,
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you get to recognize, okay, so it's this desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even I'm away from the plate of food that's still on my mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: Mentally, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's what I need to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, I do want it.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, how do I make myself not want it?
[SPEAKER_00]: But that can be only done correctly if you are first withdrawn from it with your senses.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because if you're not, doesn't matter what you're contemplating, your senses still keep you connected to it in that wrong way through the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if somebody is withdrawn and it's not going back to it, by sight, sound, smell, taste, touches, to the the most desirous thing, then recognizes that he wants it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_00]: How do I undermine the want?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, by taking the same images of this desirous thing and basically contemplating into them a non-desiring aspect, which is there, of the same thing, not something else.
[SPEAKER_00]: Within that same thing you want it, you have to find the aspects of the same thing that are not wanted.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, at the same time, you do have this desire, that you are then actively undermining through the contemplation of that same thing, aspects of the same thing, that are factually not desirable.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, if there is an attraction to a body,
[SPEAKER_00]: through the pleasure that you can get through the body.
[SPEAKER_00]: You can't just, oh, I'll get rid of this, I'll replace it with a disgust, and just, just look at this, and get this shock effect, and then I'll stop thinking about it.
[SPEAKER_00]: That won't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will work initially, novelty will run off, and you're back to where you started.
[SPEAKER_00]: Plus now, you think a super doesn't work.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you, when you recognize that desire, if it's endured, and you're not trying to get rid of it,
[SPEAKER_00]: You do find factual disgusting aspects of the same body and leave them there with the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to force the desire out with... by pushing it out with these other now contemplated aspects.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just leave the disgust, however faint it might be, leave it there with the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will neutralize it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's the point.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's like finding the balance, tuning it rightly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because, again, if you do recognize the disgusting parts, and now you want to force them even quicker to get rid of the desire, but you'll be doing that through the desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you kind of fail from the middle ground, from the middle way.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And now you realize in the broad terms, whenever there is attraction to the body, at the same time, there will be a...
[SPEAKER_00]: An aspect that is factually non-attractive, simultaneous with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's what you get to see.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, all you need to do is attend to the aspect that's non-attractive and refuse to attend to the aspect that's attractive.
[SPEAKER_00]: Both are in your mind simultaneously present.
[SPEAKER_00]: But you do not attend to those that are agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: You attend to the factually disagreeable and that's it.
[SPEAKER_00]: And if there is an impulse to do it harder, to do more of it, to do it quicker, well, you also refrain from that impulse.
[SPEAKER_00]: Just attend it rightly and leave it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It will do its work.
[SPEAKER_01]: Because that's the thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, I would say...
[SPEAKER_01]: I mean, it's kind of a common thread with nearly all of the the hindrances.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, say, this... the aspects that are non-desirable are not something that require your
[SPEAKER_01]: Input to keep feeding them.
[SPEAKER_01]: They're just there on their own.
[SPEAKER_01]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_01]: Whereas, and it's the exact opposite with the... Well, they need to be discerned there on their own, from the thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's something like you have to start enduring that thing on, that desire on the mental level first.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because that's where you're going to find these non-attractive aspects of it.
[SPEAKER_00]: If you're refusing to endure it, and then seeking the non-attractive aspects, they're all going to be rooted in aversion towards this, I just want to get rid of this thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: And it's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if it's endured correctly,
[SPEAKER_00]: Without, as I said, blindly aversive trying to just get rid of desire because it's painful.
[SPEAKER_00]: No.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bear the pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, the aspects that are factually not attractive, you know you're supposed to look for them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now you can look in that very desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: While desire is pressuring you, that's fine.
[SPEAKER_00]: All I need to do is not go back to Saitama's mental statutes associated with it.
[SPEAKER_00]: This pressure can go forever as far as I'm concerned.
[SPEAKER_00]: It can't make me act unless I choose to.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, it's unpleasant.
[SPEAKER_00]: While that's there, you start to look at the factually disgusting aspects of the same very thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: Discerning them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, while you're pressured to consume that plate, you're discerning that somebody is constantly spitting in it.
[SPEAKER_00]: But there is still desire to eat it.
[SPEAKER_00]: You still feel that hunger, but you remain attending to the knowledge that somebody spat in it, that it's contaminated, that it is soiled, and you will lose desire towards it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not overnight, but you don't have to worry about that.
[SPEAKER_01]: That's what I meant.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's not...
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, it's something you have to notice, basically, these non-desired aspects.
[SPEAKER_01]: Not something that you have to necessarily, I think, be like...
[SPEAKER_01]: But if you're kind of creating, trying to create it and fabricate it, that's going to be...
[SPEAKER_01]: I think, is that kind of what you meant?
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_01]: If you try to fabricate it...
[SPEAKER_00]: Coming out of the aversion towards the pressure of desire, it's not going to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: And there is... those aspects, everybody knows them.
[SPEAKER_00]: Usually, you find them after you try to satisfy your desires.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you're disgusted because you overate.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, people experience disgust in regard to the same things they're attracted to.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just don't know how to experience it at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, we're back onto that practice of simultaneity.
[SPEAKER_00]: Again, you get the desire, you're not trying to get rid of it, you just try to bring out a broader context of disgust, while desire is pressuring you.
[SPEAKER_00]: And leave it there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Leave that balance there, lasting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because many people would have experienced something they really want, and then get it, and then, oh, well, that was it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Or,
[SPEAKER_00]: Or even worse, they go through great lengths to obtain what they want, to consume what they want, to sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, and then they burn out all that effort, and then they have it, and then they're disgusted with it, disgusted with themselves.
[SPEAKER_00]: They just feel like, oh, this is depressing.
[SPEAKER_00]: But they feel it after.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, next time the desire comes, they're gonna seek it again.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because they won't be making the effort to bring up the factual disgusting aspects of their thing, that they have experienced, after desire would have subsided, and bring it together at the same time, while the pressure is there.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, because pressure, being uncomfortable, will kind of make them lose perspective, eh... out of aversion, to try to get rid of that discomfort and pain.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's that practice in the suttas described.
[SPEAKER_00]: He doesn't grasp the signs and the features that would be incitive of lust and take him in that direction, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you do have the desire, you do have the pressure, you're having images in your mind, and that's where you're making that choice.
[SPEAKER_00]: Am I allowing and grasping signs and features that are associated with desire and attractive aspects?
[SPEAKER_00]: Or do I refuse to, basically, allow my mind to dwell on those and proliferate, but instead, I feed it the context of the discussed, in regard to the same desire, that's still felt, that I'm not just trying to get rid and replace with... through a random practice of meditation method or technique?
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's why the organs and so on, because if they are seen on that level, like as a simultaneous,
[SPEAKER_00]: Think phenomena present there with the desire towards the thing that's comprised of those organs, then it will be very efficient.
[SPEAKER_00]: It won't be just like, yes, kidney, liver, lungs, as people just recite magically, like a magical mantra.
[SPEAKER_00]: No, it will be, oh, a bag of skin.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter how specific your desire might have been, how strong, this completely kind of just deflates it, if sustained long enough.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, those organs listed, they're pretty much universal to anything, any body, yours or others, any desire involved in between the two.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it doesn't matter the occasion, doesn't matter the specific scenario, liver, kidney, brain, bile, urine, pus, skin, hair,
[SPEAKER_00]: It's there.
[SPEAKER_00]: It has to be there, as a necessary basis.
[SPEAKER_00]: So...
[SPEAKER_00]: But, I desire it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yes, there is a desire towards the specific form that those things have taken.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now, bring up the aspects of those things that are there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Bring up the aspects of, yeah, just imagine holding a kidney or a bloody lung in your hand.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like, oh, okay, put it simultaneously there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Don't try to replace one with the other and leave that set up there.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, the disgust will work to the extent that it needs to work.
[SPEAKER_00]: You know, it's like trying to neutralize acid with alkaline.
[SPEAKER_00]: Alkaline will neutralize only acid parts.
[SPEAKER_00]: Acid drops, you pour the alkaline, it will only react with the parts that are acid.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to react with other things.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not going to destroy everything else.
[SPEAKER_01]: And then, you can just wash everything away.
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, it reminds me a bit of the verses, eh...
[SPEAKER_01]: One of the verses I really like in the Therigata from the nuns, where...
[SPEAKER_01]: So, it's like the nun is walking in the forest or something, and some guy comes and is, like, I don't know, harassing her and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he's saying, oh, come with me, come and marry me, and you'll be dressed and find clothes and everything, and leave this house, this life.
[SPEAKER_01]: And she asks him, what do you find so attractive?
[SPEAKER_01]: In this, in this body, in this microphone, he says, oh, your eyes, your eyes are like a doll.
[SPEAKER_01]: And it's so beautiful and so on.
[SPEAKER_01]: Oh, really?
[SPEAKER_01]: Okay.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, if it's my eyes you want, and then she takes out the eye.
[SPEAKER_01]: And so, here you go.
[SPEAKER_01]: And he was shocked and disgusted.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, so, it's the same, like you were saying, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_01]: But, like, in and of itself, nobody wants it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it's the form and the shape where the attraction rests.
[SPEAKER_00]: In and of itself, that which makes that shape and form, it's like, ooh, but that's not seen at the same time.
[SPEAKER_00]: And also, like, a person doesn't need to go and actively seek out the attraction to practice asubha in regard to it, because if you have not... Well, if you're not free from passion, means even without any specific things coming up your mind... coming up like... sort of like desire taking over your mind, even without any specific sight, sound, smell, taste, touch or image, you are within that domain.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in other words, you do carry that basis for attraction with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: You don't go around and, when you see the body, when the body pops up, do you first see the disgusting aspect naturally, or do you first see the attractive aspect naturally?
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, if it's not the the former, means you do carry your lust with you.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, you could start practicing this asubha anytime, on that right level.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, it does not require a specific arousal, or desire, or this, to counter it.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, fundamentally, you go around carrying a view that bodies are not disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's... that's the first thing you see.
[SPEAKER_00]: Then, you try to see the asubha and so on, but for as long as that order is not changed up, whereby the view is that the bodies are disgusting, as in, like, not just intellectual idea, but when the bodies are experienced in the way that could be provocative of desire, well, it's provocative of disgust, not desire.
[SPEAKER_00]: Same.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you would not be disgusted with the thing that's on the plate that you don't deem edible.
[SPEAKER_00]: But if somebody offers you to eat it, then it's like, whoa, no.
[SPEAKER_00]: Now it's genuinely disgusting.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you brought up that context.